<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevv Englands teares, for old Englands feares. Preached in a sermon on July 23. 1640. being a day of publike humiliation, appointed by the churches in behalfe of our native countrey in time of feared dangers. / By William Hooke, minister of Gods Word; sometime of Axmouth in Devonshire, now of Taunton in New England. Sent over to a worthy member of the honourable House of Commons, who desires it may be for publick good.</title>
            <author>Hooke, William, 1600 or 1601-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E208_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860216</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860216</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86519)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 37:E208[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevv Englands teares, for old Englands feares. Preached in a sermon on July 23. 1640. being a day of publike humiliation, appointed by the churches in behalfe of our native countrey in time of feared dangers. / By William Hooke, minister of Gods Word; sometime of Axmouth in Devonshire, now of Taunton in New England. Sent over to a worthy member of the honourable House of Commons, who desires it may be for publick good.</title>
                  <author>Hooke, William, 1600 or 1601-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.P. for Iohn Rothwell and Henry Overton, and are to be sould at the Sunne in Pauls Church-yard, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job II, 13 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112333:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEVV ENGLANDS TEARES, FOR OLD ENGLANDS FEARES.</p>
            <p>Preached in a Sermon on <hi>July</hi> 23. 1640. being a day of Publike Humiliation, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Churches in behalfe of our Native Countrey in time of feared dangers.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM HOOKE, Miniſter of GODS Word; Sometime of <hi>Axmouth</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> now of <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>New England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sent over to a worthy Member of the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of Commons, who deſires it may be for publick good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Rothwell</hi> and <hi>Henry Overton,</hi> and are to be ſould at the Sunne in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and in <hi>Popes</hi>-head Alley. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112333:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112333:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COURTEOUS READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here preſented to thy view, a Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to ſome in <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for <hi>Old Englands</hi> ſake: wherein is expreſſed much love, to a Countrey left. It was once im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> that he cared not for his Countrey, becauſe he ſeemed to be little moved with the ruines thereof. This cannot be imputed to our brethren of <hi>New-England;</hi> for they, not ſeeing, nor hearing of, onely fearing the ruines of this our Countrey, were deeply affected with it; a ſigne they love us. Some have applyed that of the Apoſtle to them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. <hi>(They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us, for if they had beene of us, they would no doubt have continued with us,)</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:112333:3"/>but how falſely it is applyed, this Sermon doth diſcover: for certainly <hi>they are of us,</hi> though <hi>they be gone from us, for if they were not of us,</hi> their affections would not have ſo <hi>continued to us,</hi> as to faſt and pray for us. <hi>Amor poſcit amorem</hi> Let our affections be endeared to them.</p>
            <p>As for this Sermon, expect not care-pleaſing, but heart-affecting phraſes in it: the Author ſought not ſo much to pleaſe as to profit; nor to informe the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to worke upon the affections; If thou bring thy heart with thee to the Reading of it, thou mayſt find thy heart melting by Reading of it, and then thou ſhalt have cauſe to bleſſe GOD for it. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112333:3"/>
            <head>NEVV ENGLANDS TEARES, <hi>FOR</hi> OLD ENGLANDS FEARES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOB 2.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So they ſate downe with him upon the ground ſeven dayes and ſeven nights, and none ſpake a word unto him, for they ſaw that his griefe was very great.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE words are ſpoken of <hi>Jobs</hi> three friends, who were now come to viſite him, and ſympathize with him in the time of his diſtreſſe. They had made an appointment thus to doe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. viz. to come to mourne with him, and to comfort him. For thus the godly ſhould ſend to one another in like caſe,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112333:4"/>and acquaint one another with the ſorrowes and calamities of their friends and brethren, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to contribute and caſt in their ſorrowes and ſympathize when their friends are afflicted. A godly practice, and which the Churches in this Land doe well this day to imitate.</p>
            <p>Now then are <hi>Jobs</hi> friends comming towards him, and <hi>when they lift up their eyes a far off, they knew him not, &amp;c.</hi> Affliction may ſo alter the outward face of things and friends, that anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent acquaintance may not know them. Upon this, <hi>they ſate downe with him upon the ground, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſumme of what is now read unto you, is the ſympathy of <hi>Iobs</hi> friends in the time of his calamity; and from it we may obſerve this point,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is the part of true friends and brethren,<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> to ſympathize and fellow-feele with their brethren and friends when the hand of God is upon them.</hi> For thus, you ſee, did <hi>Iobs</hi> three friends here doe; and they performed a very brotherly office of love in ſo doing. When therefore afterwards their hearts grew more hard towards him, he cals upon them for the ſame compaſſions,<note place="margin">Iob 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>Have pity upon me, have pity upon me, O yee my friends, for the hand of the Lord hath touched mee.</hi> From whence wee may likewiſe collect, that <hi>when the hand of God hath touched a friend, all his friends ſhould have tender pity upon him.</hi> And ſuch affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions have the godly ſhewen forth, as we finde in Scripture. <hi>Who is weake,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, and I am not weake?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>Who is offended, and I burne not?</hi> When <hi>David</hi> was in great heavineſſe, as being
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112333:4"/>under a great affliction by the rebellious inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the ſonne of his owne loynes againſt him, <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Jonathan, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> deare friend, did neither dreſſe his feete,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.24,</note> nor trimme his beard, nor waſh his clothes, untill the day that the King returned in peace. And <hi>Jeremy</hi> writes a booke of Lamentations for <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dahs</hi> miſery, though himſelfe had then his life given him for a prey. When the naturall body of Chriſt was to ſuffer, he ſaid to his friends, <hi>Weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelves;</hi> but when his myſticall body ſuffers, he expects that we ſhould not weepe ſo much for our ſelves as for him.</p>
            <p>Nay, <hi>David</hi> ſympathizeth with his very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; <hi>As for me, when they were ſick, my clothing was Sack-cloth, and I humbled my ſoule by faſting; I behaved my ſelfe as though he had been my friend or brother, I bowed downe heavily as one that mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for his Mother,</hi> Pſal. 35.13, 14. Whence wee gather, what our affections and behaviours ought to be for our friends, brethren, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in their diſtreſſe. Yea, which is yet more, wee finde one wicked man fellow feeling with another. <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> a wicked King went downe to viſite wicked <hi>Joram</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ahab,</hi> becauſe he was ſick, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.27, 29. And both God and his Church and Children will complaine in the want of this brotherly affection. <hi>Among all her Lovers,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jeremy, ſhee hath none to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her,</hi> Lam. 1.2. It was indeed <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery not to be pitied, but withall it was her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112333:5"/>ſinne. Therefore ſhee complaines, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Is it nothing unto you all, ye that paſſe by? Behold and ſee, if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>I called for my Lovers, but they deceived me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> And <hi>Obadiah</hi> prophecieth againſt <hi>Edom</hi> for their cruelty, and want of compaſſion with their brethren of <hi>Judah</hi> in the day of their diſtreſſe. When Chriſt is any way afflicted, he expecteth to be pittied,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> and will openly condemn them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the world that omit this dutie. And that parabolicall ſpeech of Chriſt to the Jewes, of children ſitting in the Market place, and calling one to another,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.32.</note> and ſaying; <hi>Wee have mourned to you, and yee have not wept,</hi> is taken from this ground, that it is matter of juſt complaint, if when friends doe mourne, their fellows doe not weepe.</p>
            <p>But the Scriptures are expreſſe in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of this ſympathy.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Rejoyce with them that rejoyce, and weepe with them that weepe; be of the ſame minde one towards another.</hi> When the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle had ſaid, <hi>Let brotherly love continue;</hi> in the verſes following he inſtanceth in two duties thereof;<note place="margin">Heb. 13.1, 2, 3</note> firſt, <hi>In enterteining ſtrangers;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>In remembring them that are in bonds as bound with them, and them that ſuffer adverſitie, as being our ſelves alſo in the ſame body.</hi> God doth then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly require this part of brotherly love. The Doctrine is cleare enough, <hi>It is the part of true friends,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 17.17.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. A friend loveth at all times, and a brother is borne for adverſitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:112333:5"/>
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe they are members of the ſame body;the Reaſon intimated by the Apoſtle, <hi>Remember them that are in adverſitie, as being your ſelves alſo in the ſame body.</hi> Now it is the part of one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to fellow-feele with another. When the <hi>Shunamites</hi> ſonne was ſick, eſpecially in one part, his whole body complained, ſaying, <hi>My head,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 4.19.</note> 
                  <hi>my head.</hi> This made <hi>David</hi> to ſay <hi>for my brethren and Companions ſake, I will ſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1 22, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Peace be within thee.</hi> He deſired the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe of his brethren and companions there, who were as it were, bone of his bone.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is a great lightning of the afflictions of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to be bemoaned by brethren and friends in time of affliction. <hi>Solamem miſeris ſocios, &amp;c.</hi> ſociall ſorrowes doe ſomewhat ſolace the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Which wee ſee in <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Complaint for want of pity from her Lovers, and <hi>Jobs</hi> (at laſt) from his friends. Now it is the part of friends and fellowes to beare one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens. Yea it is of the Law of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> which is the Law of Love. And ſurely, if a man doth but ſee his horſe over-burdened, he will run preſently and lighten the loade that is upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Againe; Conſider that it may be the caſe of, friends themſelves, who then would be glad to be ſympathized with. A man that hath friends,<note place="margin">Prov. 18. laſt.</note> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> muſt carry himſelfe friendly. He may ſoone els looſe his friends when he expects
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112333:6"/>to be dealt with friendly by them. One reaſon why <hi>mercy rejoyceth againſt judgement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.13.</note> is becauſe as it hath yeelded mercy to others in time of Judgement, ſo now it expects the ſame from them in like caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, It is an eaſie ſervice of Love. It coſt <hi>Jobs</hi> friends but little to come and beſtow their teares and their ſorrowes upon him. What can a friend doe leſſe? true friendſhip and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood goes further, it will, nay it muſt, if need be, lay downe its life for the brethren.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.16.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Before I come to the maine uſe which I ayme at, I will ſpeake a few words, by way of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to ſhew how farre they are from being friends or brethren, who are ready to rejoyce at the afflictions and miſeries of others. A right E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domitiſh quality;<note place="margin">Obad. verſ. 12.</note> for <hi>Edom</hi> rejoyced over the children of <hi>Judah</hi> in the day of their deſtruction, and ſpake proudly in the day of their diſtreſſe: and theſe were a curſed generation. And indeed the Pſalmiſt implyes it to be a property of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects thus to doe: <hi>In mine adverſity they rejoyced,<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.15.</note> and gathered themſelves together, yea the abjects,</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> the caſt-awayes) <hi>gathered themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And it is commonly obſerved, that men and women who have turned Witches, and been in league with the devill, thereby to doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, are never given over ſo to doe, till they begin to have an evill eye, which grieveth at the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112333:6"/>Proſperity, and rejoyceth at the miſery of others. Hence Witchcraſt is deſcribed by an evill eye.</p>
               <p>I know not what eye hath bewitched my young Lambes. And when any are bewitched,<note place="margin">Neſcio quis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neros oculus mihi faſcina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> agnos.</note> it is a phraſe of ſpeech among many to ſay, they are overſeene, <hi>i.e.</hi> lookt upon with a malicious eye. Nay, it is the property of the devill to be thus affected. Mans proſperity is his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine, and mans adverſity his rejoyeing, as wee ſee in <hi>Iob;</hi> neither is there (ſcarce) any thing that doth more import the ſeed of the Serpent in a man, then this ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> rejoycing in the evill and miſery of another. It is then the property of Edomites, abjects, witches and devils, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the miſery that befalleth others. And though I am not able to charge any of you with this curſed affection, yet I doe wiſh you to looke into your owne hearts; for this I am ſure, here are ſtrong temptations ſometimes, leading to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it in this Land, which when they meet with an heart voyd of grace, muſt needs ſtirre up the diſpoſition in it, and not onely emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and envyings, but witchcraft it ſelfe is a worke of the fleſh.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.19, 20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But the uſe that I doe principally intend, is of Exhortation to you all, as you deſire to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveyour ſelves the true friends and brethren of your deare Countrey-men in old <hi>England,</hi> to condole with them this day in their afflictions. <hi>Jobs</hi> friends, you ſee, did it for him ſeven dayes and ſeven nights, <hi>i.e.</hi> many dayes, oh let us doe it then this one day, at leaſt, for theſe.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:112333:7"/>
               <p>Indeed when we looke upon our ſelves at this time in this Land, the Lord hath given us great cauſe of rejoycing, both in reſpect of civill and ſpirituall peace. God hath at once ſubdued the proud <hi>Pequats</hi> and the proud opinions that roſe up in this Land; and for plenty, never had the Land the like. Yea, which is much better, the Word of God growes and multiplyeth;<note place="margin">Act. 12.</note> the Churches have reſt throughout the whole land, and are edified,<note place="margin">Act. 9.31.</note> and walking in the feare of the Lord and in the comfort of the holy Ghoſt, are multiplyed. This is much, and more it would be, if the edge of theſe and other our comforts were not this day turned by the feare of civill ſtrifes and combuſtions in the Land of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie, which doe not a little abate the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all other our happineſſe to us, and call for Lamentation and ſack cloth at our hands.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Why is thy countenance ſad, ſeeing thou art not ſicke?</hi> Have you not read the anſwer? <hi>Why ſhould not my countenance be ſad, when the City, the place of my Fathers ſepulchres lyes waſt, and the gates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are conſumed with fire?</hi> Why? <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was well enough at eaſe, he had honour, and power, and favour, and pleaſure enough, and being the Kings Cup-bearer, he had Wine enough of all ſorts at his command, which maketh glad the heart of man. But what is all this not to cloud his countenance, and to overcaſt it with griefe and ſorrow, when the City of his Fathers was layd waſt, and the gates thereof conſumed with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112333:7"/>fire? Thus Beloved, if our comforts were treble to what they are this day, yet could it not but much abate the ſweetneſſe of them, to conſider what diſtreſſes may lie at this time upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countrey, for ought wee know, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have too juſt cauſe to feare. When the Arke and Iſrael and Judah abode in tents, and <hi>Joab</hi> and his men were encamped in the open fields,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.11.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rijah</hi> tooke no comfort in his beautifull wiſe, nor in his houſe, nor in his meate and drinke.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore, I beſeech you, lay aſide the though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of all our comforts this day, and let us f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſten our eyes upon the calamities of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in old <hi>England,</hi> calamities, at leaſt, immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent calamities dropping, ſwords that have hung along time over their heads by a twine thread, judgements long ſince threatned as foreſeene by many of Gods Meſſengers in the cauſes, though not foretold by a Spirit prophetically guided; heavy judgements in all probability when they fall, if they are not fallen already. And not to looke upon the occaſions given on the one ſide or the other, betweene the two Siſter Nations (Siſter Nations? ah, the word woundeth,) let us looke this day ſimply on the event, a ſad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in all likelihood, the dividing of a King from his Subjects, and him from them, their mutuall taking up of Armes in oppoſition and deſence; the conſequences, even the gloomy and darke conſequences thereof, are killing and ſlaying, and ſacking and burning, and robbing and rifting, curſing and blaſpheming, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112333:8"/>
               <p>If you ſhould but ſee Warre deſcribed to you in a Map, eſpecially in a Countrey well knowne to you, nay dearely beloved of you, where you drew your firſt breath, where once, yea where lately you dwelt, where you have received ten thouſand mercies, and have many a deare friend and Countrey-man and kinſman abiding, how could you but lament and mourne?</p>
               <p>Warre is the conflict of enemies enraged with bloody revenge, wherein the parties oppoſite carry their lives in their hands, every man tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prodigall of his very heart blood, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be killed to kill. The inſtruments are cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing ſwords, ratling ſpeares, skul-dividing Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beards, murthering pieces, and thundering Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, from whoſe mouths proceed the fire and ſmell and ſmoake and terrour and death, as it were, of the very bottomleſſe pit. Wee wonder now and then at the ſudden death of a man; alas, you might there ſee a thouſand men not onely healthy, but ſtout and ſtrong, ſtruck dead in the twinckling of an eye, their breath exhales with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us.</hi> Death heweth its way thorow a wood of men in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of time from the mouth of a murderer, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a forreſt into a champion ſuddenly; and when it hath uſed theſe to ſlay their oppoſites, they are recompenced with the like death them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>O the ſhrill care-piercing clangs of the trumpets, noiſe of drums, the animating voices of Horſe Captains and Commanders, learned and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to deſtroy!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 39.19, 20, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>There is the undaunted horſe whoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112333:8"/>neck is clothed with thunder, and the glory of whoſe noſtrills is terrible; how doth he lye pawing and praunſing in the valley going forth to meet the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men? he mocks at feare, ſwallowing the ground with fiercenes and rage, and ſaying among the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, Ha, Ha, he ſmels the battell a far off, the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Captaines and the ſhouting.</hi> Here ride ſome dead men ſwagging in their deep ſaddles; there fall others alive upon their dead horſes; death ſends a meſſage to thoſe from the mouth of the Muskets, theſe it talkes with face to face, and ſtabbs them in the fiſt rib: In yonder file there is a man hath his arme ſtruck off from his ſhoulder, another by him hath loſt his leg; here ſtands a Souldier with halfe a face, there fights another upon his ſtrumps, and at once both kils and is killed; not far off lyes a company wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their ſweat and goare; ſuch a man whileſt he chargeth his Musket is diſcharg'd of his life, and falls upon his dead fellow.<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> Every battell of the warriour is with confuſed noiſe and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rouled in blood. Death reignes in the field, and is ſure to have the day which ſide ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver falls. In the meane while (ô formidable!) the infernall fiends follow the Campe to catch after the ſoules of rude nefarious ſouldiers (ſuch as are commonly men of that calling) who fight themſelves feareleſly into the mouth of hell for revenge, a booty, or a little revenue. How thick and threefold doe they ſpeed one another to deſtruction? A day of battell is a day of harveſt for the devill.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112333:9"/>
               <p>All this while, the poore wife and tender children ſit weeping together at home, having taken their late farewell of the harneſſed huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and father (ô it was a ſad parting if you had ſeene it!) never looking to ſee his face againe, as indeed many and the moſt of them never doe; for anon comes <hi>Ely's</hi> meſſenger from the Camp, ſaying,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a great ſlanghter among the people, and your husband is dead, your father is dead, he was ſlaine in an hot fight, he was ſhot dead in the place and never ſpake a word more.</hi> Then the poore widow who fed yet upon a crumb of hope, teares her haire from her head, rends her cloths, wrings her hands, lifts up her voice to heaven, and weeps like <hi>Rachell</hi> that would not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, her children hang about her crying and ſaying, O my father is ſlaine, my father is dead, I ſhall never ſee my father more; and ſo they cry and ſob and ſight out their afflicted ſoules, and breake their hearts together. Alas, Alas! this is yet but Warre thorow a Creviſe. Beloved, doe but conſider; There is many times fire without warre, and famine and peſtilence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warre, but warre is never without them: and there are many times robberies without warre, and murthering of paſſengers, raviſhing of matrones, deflouring of virgins, cruelties and torments and ſometimes barbarous and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane practices without warre, but warre goes ſeldome or never without them.</p>
               <p>Warre, it is <hi>malum complexum,</hi> a compound of Judgements,<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.8.</note> amixt miſery, <hi>the cup in the hand
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112333:9"/>of the Lord, the wine whereof is red, and it is full of mixture.</hi> The wine is indeed as red as blood, and the ingredients are fire, famine, peſtilence, murthers, robberies, rapes, deflourings, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, torments, with many other miſeries. The voice of melody ceaſeth, relations that were lately the comfort are now become the griefe of the life of men; <hi>the high wayes are unoccupyed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudges 5.6, 7, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the travellers walke thorow by wayes, the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the villages ceaſe, and the noiſe of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers is heard in the places of drawing water.</hi> Warre, it is the immediate hand of ſuch whoſe tendereſt mercies are cruelties,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.14.</note> commonly therefore the laſt of Gods ſtroakes upon them that will take no warning. But yet there is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in warres; a warre in the borders of an enemy is held better then a warre in ones native Countrey; for commonly, the land that is as the garden of <hi>Eden</hi> before an enemy,<note place="margin">Joel 2.3.</note> behind them is like a deſolate Wilderneſſe; and it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wofull when people and land ſhall be waſted together. Or if it be warre in our owne and, yet a warre againſt a forreigne enemy invading, is far better then a civill warre. It is grievous, but not admirable, to ſee an Egyptian and an Hebrew contending, but to ſee, as the Prophet ſayth, Egyptians againſt Egyptians,<note place="margin">Iſa. 19.2.</note> and every one fighting againſt his brother, and againſt his neighbour, City againſt City, and Kingdome againſt Kingdome; or to ſee, as the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſayth, <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.21.</note> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah;</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:112333:10"/>O, this is both lamentable and wonderfull! The mad Souldier in the heart of his blood, and the depth of his Atheiſme, may account it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps at firſt with <hi>Abner</hi> but a play, to ſee Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites catching of Iſraelites by the beard,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.14, 15, 16.</note> and thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting their ſwords in one anothers ſides: but of all warres none ſo bloody, neither hath any play ſuch bitterneſſe in the end.</p>
               <p>It is a ſad play, wherein not onely mens goods and bodyes and ſoules doe commonly lye at ſtake, but wherein alſo even the very Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is conquered, as one that played but for his owne money, and at ſuch a deſperate play whoſe very gaines are looſings. No warres ſo cruell, ſo unnaturall, ſo deſolating, as civill warres. You have heard, Beloved, of the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full German-warres; why, if there be any in our owne Countrey this day, I may call them Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-warres, becauſe they are the warres of Germans, even the bloody contentions of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; and when relations turne oppoſites, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more oppoſite. A Kingdome at warres with a forreigne enemy may ſtand, but a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome divided againſt it ſelfe, can never; there can never be proſperitie within <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.7.</note> if firſt there be not peace within her walls. Unity and peace are a bond,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note> and where that is broken, there muſt needs follow diſſolution.</p>
               <p>When the Philiſtines went beating downe one another,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.16.</note> 
                  <hi>the multitude</hi> (mark the word) <hi>mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away.</hi> A thing never conſumes faſter, then when it falls to melting: and how doe ſuch wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112333:10"/>themſelves for an enemy without, and ſight for the conqueſt of ſome forreigne adverſary? <hi>Gedeons</hi> men may ſtand ſtill every man in his place,<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.21.22.</note> ſo long as Midianites turne their ſwords againſt Midianites.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.</note> Neither needs <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> ſtrike a ſtroake, when the Moabites, Ammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites and Edomites his enemies, lye in ambuſh one againſt another; firſt <hi>Moah</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt <hi>Edom,</hi> and then <hi>Moah</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> one againſt another. And what was the iſſue of the eleven Tribes warres with their brother <hi>Benjamin,</hi> but lamentation,<note place="margin">Iudg 21.2, 3, 6.</note> mourning and woe? And yet too among civill warres,<note place="margin">—En quò diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia cives Perduxit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeros.</note> ſome are worſe then other. I have read, I remember, in <hi>Lucan,</hi> of warres betweene <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> worſe then civill:<note place="margin">Bellaper Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theospluſquam civilia campos.</note> and ſuch eſpecially are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tining warres, when there is little truſt to either ſide, and friends are ſcarce knowne from foes, but all things are filled with conjurations, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, diſtractions, factions, feares, ſuſpitions, tumults, combuſtions, ſpoy lings, &amp;c. The Lord be mercifull to old <hi>England,</hi> as hitherto he hath been, yea more then to any Land this day un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne, which indeed heightneth its ſins above the Sunne, and makes it more ſinfull then any Land at this time in the whole world, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that we cannot but yeeld that there are no warres that <hi>Englands</hi> ſinnes have not deſerved. Let us therefore feare the worſt at this preſent in behalfe of our deare Countrey-men (conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring alſo what ill tidings we have heard thence) that nothing, as we doubt, but a miracle of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112333:11"/>power and mercy can preſerve them from the miſeries of the devouring ſword. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what the Auxiliaries of Egypt ſaid in their diſtreſſe,<note place="margin">Jere. 46.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſe, and let us goe againe unto our people, and to the Land of our Nativity from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing ſword;</hi> but if wee were now under that miſery, I doubt it would be in vaine for us to ſay the like. But that which wee are now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto, is Brotherly Compaſſion, and to doe the part of <hi>Jobs</hi> friends in my Text, to ſit aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as at the crying ſinnes, ſo at the feared ſorrowes of our Countrymen, for in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, their griefe is very great.</p>
               <p>To this end, you may thinke a while upon theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Of our civill relation to that Land, and the Inhabitants therein. There is no Land that claimes our name, but <hi>England,</hi> wee are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from all the Nations in the world by the name of <hi>Engliſh.</hi> There is no Potentate breathing, that wee call our dread Soveraigne, but King CHARLES, nor Lawes of any Land have civilized us, but <hi>Englands;</hi> there is no Nation that calls us Countrey-men, but the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Brethren! Did wee not there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aw in our firſt breath? Did not the Sunne firſt ſhine there upon our heads? Did not that Land firſt beare us, even that pleaſant Iſland, but for ſin, I would ſay, that Garden of the Lord, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Withall, let us thinke upon our naturall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to many in that Land. Some of you, I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112333:11"/>know, have Fathers and Mothers there, ſome of you have Brethren and Siſters, others of you have Uncles and Aunts there, and neare kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke. All theſe ſitting in griefe and ſorrow, challenge our ſympathize; and it is a fearefull ſin to be voyde of naturall affections:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.31.</note> nature wrought in <hi>Abraham,</hi> as well as grace, when his nephew <hi>Lot</hi> was taken captive by the foure Kings.<note place="margin">Gen. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But which is more, let us remember, how(for many of us) we ſtand in a ſpirituall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to many, yea very many in that Land. The ſame threed of grace is ſpun thorow the hearts of all the godly under heaven. Such a one there, is thy ſpirituall Father, he begot thee in Chriſt Jeſus thorow the Goſpell; and there thou haſt ſpirituall Brethren and Siſters and Mothers.<note place="margin">Matth. 12.50.</note> O there is many a ſweet, loving, humble, heavenly ſoule in that Land, in whoſe boſome Chriſt breaths by his bleſſed Spirit every day, and ſuch as I hope wee ſhall ever love at the remoteſt diſtance, were it from one end of the earth unto the other. Why, they are bone of our bone, and fleſh of our fleſh in Chriſt, nearer by farre then friends, and kindred, oh let their ſorrowes be our ſorrowes, and their miſeries ours.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Beſides theſe relations, civill, naturall, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,let us thinke upon the ſpeciall tyes and and engagements that many there have upon us. Among your friends there, whither naturall or ſpirituall, there are, no doubt, ſome there,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112333:12"/>whom you prize above the reſt. O if you could but ſee them, your ſoules would hardly ſtay within your bodies for running forth to meet them; At leſt, you would ſtrive to incorporate your ſelves into them by the cloſeſt embraces. Alas, theſe now, perhaps, are weeping in their ſecret places, theſe are now ſitting with <hi>Job</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the aſhes. If you could but ſee the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of their ſorrowes, and heare their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſpeeches and complaints, and how they, their wives, and little ones doe ſit and lament to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, it may be ſome of them in expectation of daily death, and how they faſt and pray, and afflict their ſoules, or how, peradventure, they wiſh themſelves at this very inſtant with us; O you would weepe and cry, and melt away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to teares of ſorrow.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> To this, adde the Conſideration of the many mercies, heapes of rich and precious mercies, twenty, yea thirty and forty yeares mercies, and to ſome more, which wee have there received; eſpecially ſoule mercies. There the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus firſt ſhined forth unto thee; there firſt thou heardſt his pleaſant voice; there did his good Spirit firſt breathe upon thine heart; there didſt thou firſt beleeve and repent, and amend thy lewd wayes. And never was there a Land, I thinke, ſince Chriſt and his Apoſtles left the world, ſo richly bleſt in converts, or that ever brought forth ſuch and ſo many worthies into the world. Yet there now (alas indeed, where ſooner, when ſinne
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112333:12"/>aboundeth?) doth Judgement begin to reigne, as we may greatly feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Or is it not meet that we ſhould beare a partwith them in their ſorrowes, who have borne a part with them in their ſinnes? Have we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred ſo many ſinnes as we have done to ſpeed on their confuſion, and ſhall we beſtow no ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row on them? Shall we not help to quench the fire with our teares, that we have kindled with our ſinnes? O cruell! How know wee but that the Lord is at this inſtant viſiting our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions there acted, which polluted the Land? Beloved, did wee not commit there ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand millions of ſinnes and more amongſt us du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our aboad there? There, O there, we play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ungodly Atheiſts, there it was we halted betweene God and <hi>Baal,</hi> ſware by the Lord and by <hi>Malchom,</hi> were neither hot nor cold; there ſome of us blaſphemed the dreadfull name of the ever bleſſed God, polluted his Sabbaths, deſpiſed his meſſengers, contemned his holy wayes, prophaned and abuſed his mercies, and his good creatures, ran with others to the ſame exceſſe of riot, &amp;c. And how ever ſome may ſay, they have repented hereof, yet little doe they know what evill examples they have left there behind to fill up the meaſure both of ſinne and wrath. If thy ſinnes committed there be pardoned, yet thy ſins ſins may be puniſhed, like as a Father may be ſpared, and yet his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren executed.</p>
               <p>Thy ſinnes; ôman, have begotten many ſins
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112333:13"/>there; there is many a formaliſt, and many a conformitant the more for thee, as indeed I feare there is for me. Alas, how have they kept on ſinning upon our examples? Anothers drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſes have begotten many a drunkard there, as anothers ſpirituall cowardize many a Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, and anothers Lukewarmeneſſe many a <hi>Laodicean.</hi> Now, doe we feare that the Lord is gone forth this day to call that Land to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and to viſite for theſe and the like abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and is this nothing unto us? Shall men be ſlaine for our ſinnes, and we afford them no ſorrow? What? ſhall the old Prophet in <hi>Bethel</hi> riſe up in judgement againſt us? for when he had ſlaine the man of God by his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſſembling to him, he yet mourned and lamented over him,<note place="margin">1 King. 13.30.</note> ſaying, <hi>Alas my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Ah my friends and brethren, let us doe the like; our ſinnes have ſlaine, perhaps by this time, a little Army of men, what can wee leſſe then lament over them, ſaying, <hi>Alas, Alas, our Brethren.</hi> Surely, wee in this Land have great cauſe to doe as wee doe this day, if for no other reſpect, yet for this; for wee have done enough and enough to overwhelme old <hi>England</hi> with the wrath of God; that our hearts at this time could be but over-ſhadowed with a cloud of ſorrow!</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Againe; let us ſuppoſe that things were even now turned end for end, and that wee were this day in diſtreſſe, and thoſe our brethren in peace; I am confident, that they would condole with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112333:13"/>us, yea and powre out many a prayer for us: for they did as much, I know, when this Land lay ſometimes under dearth, another time when the Indians rebelled, a third, when the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous opinions prevailed. And how have they alwayes liſſened after our wellfare, ebbing and flowing in their affections with us? How doe they (I meane all this while, multitudes of well affected perſons there) talke of <hi>New-England</hi> with delight! How much nearer heaven doe ſome of their charities account this Land, then any other place they heare of in the world? Such is their good opinion of us! How have ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them deſired to dye, if they might not be vouchſafed to live in this Land? And when ſometimes a <hi>New-England</hi> man returnes thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how is he lookt upon, lookt after, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, entertained, the ground he walks upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved for his ſake, and the houſe held the better where he is? how are his words liſſened to, laid up, and related frequently when he is gone? neither is any love or kindneſſe held too much for ſuch a man.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Neither let this be forgotten, that of all theChriſtian people this day in the world, wee in this Land enjoy the greateſt meaſure of peace and tranquilitie. Wee have beaten our ſwords into plough-ſhares and our ſpeares into pruning hookes, when others have beaten their pruning hookes into ſpeares, and their plough-ſhares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſword. And now, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayd to the Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benites and the Gadites,<note place="margin">Numb. 32.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Shall your brethren goe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112333:14"/>to warre, and ſhall yee ſit ſtill?</hi> So, ſhall our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren goe to warre, and we ſit ſtill, and not ſo much as grieve with them? ſhall they be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the ſword and ſpeare, and not we pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo much as with brotherly ſorrow? Surely then, if ever the LORD ſhould bring the like houre of temptation upon us, as his people here have not been long hitherto without exerciſe, he might juſtly ſhut us out of the hearts of all our brethren in the world. And whereas too perhaps here and there one in our native Land, eſpecially in their paſſions, may have had ſome tranſient thoughts, touching, it may be, ſome of us, as if the exorbitant ſpirit of <hi>John</hi> and <hi>James</hi> were in us, deſirous that fire from heaven ſhould fall upon them, as if, I meane, we would be glad to heare of Judgements upon our native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey (ô cruell, and unnaturall!) our fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings this day, I hope, ſhall wipe away all ſuch prejudices. And truly, if Gods Juſtice might be ſatisfied with that Lands amendment without one drop of blood, though we ſhould ſhed ſtore both of teares and blood to effect it, wee would greatly rejoyce, and ſoone turne this day of Humiliation into a day of gratulation, graiſe, and thankeſgiving.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> What ſhall I ſay? If there ſhould be any one heart here digd out of a Marpelian rock, let ſuch an one remember,<note place="margin">Iere. 29.7.</note> laſtly, that in the peace of that Land, we ſhall have peace, and therefore in the miſery of that Land, we ſhall never be happie. You know, that God hath hitherto made that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112333:14"/>Land a bleſſing unto this; If Chriſt hath a Vine here, that Land hath as yet been the Elme that hath ſuſteined it. Thence hath the Lord thus ſtockt this American part with ſuch Worthies, there were they bred and nurſt, thence hitherto have been our yearely ſupplies of men, and of many an uſefull commoditie. If then they ſuffer, we may eaſily ſmart; if they ſink, wee are not likely to riſe. And this, at leaſt, may be a perſwaſive to a ſordide minde, that will not be wrought upon by more ingenuous Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>The mercifull God ſtirre up all our affections, and give us that godly ſympathy, which that Land deſerveth at our hands, and teach us to expreſſe it upon all occaſions of ill tydings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to our eares from thence. Yea, let us ſit at this time like old <hi>Ely</hi> upon the wayes ſide,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.</note> wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, as he did, for the Arke of the Lord, with a trembling hand and heart. And let us be every day confeſſing of our old <hi>England</hi> ſinnes, of its high pride, Idolatry, ſuperſtition, blaſphemies, blood, cruelties, Atheiſmes, &amp;c. and let us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver goe to our ſecrets without our Cenſors in our hands for old <hi>England,</hi> deare <hi>England</hi> ſtill in diverſe reſpects, left indeed by us in our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but never yet forſaken in our affections. The good God of Heaven, have mercy upon it, and upon all his deare people and ſervants in it, for Chriſt his ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
